Finding Aid for Charles F. Cannell papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles F. Cannell papers 1946-2001 1974-1998
Cannell, Charles F.
07138 Aa 2
Charles Cannell was a social scientist, professor, and co-founder of the Survey Research Center at the University of Michigan. Papers consist of project files, research proposals and grant applications, conference presentations, teaching material, and biographical information, the majority of which span 1974 to 1998. The bulk of the collection represents work on an array of projects regarding interviewing and survey methodology, including several projects on the use of technology, such as the telephone, in the interviewing process.
2.5 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 8680 ) was received in two accessions, January1998 and January 2002.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Charles Frederick Cannell was born on September 10, 1913 in Antrim, New Hampshire. He received his B.A. from the University of New Hampshire in 1936 and began his doctoral studies in clinical psychology two years later at the Ohio State University. After the United States entered World War II, Cannell interrupted his doctoral studies and moved to Washington D.C., where he began work at the Division of Program Studies in the Department of Agriculture. By the end of his time at the department, Cannell had risen to the position of field staff director for the Program Studies Division, which had developed into a general survey facility for the government.
In 1946 Cannell moved to Ann Arbor and joined the faculty of the University of Michigan. Along with Rensis Likert and Angus Campbell, Cannell was among the first generation of researchers who founded the Survey Research Center (SRC), a division of the university's Institute for Social Research. Cannell helped to establish the SRC as one of the first national interviewing facilities in the United States. Cannell also restarted his dissertation, receiving his doctoral degree from Ohio State in 1952.
Cannell was most known for his work in methodological research. While at the University of Michigan, his research focused on understanding the psychology of the survey process, the reliability of survey data, and variables acting on interviewers and respondents. Along with many articles and chapters he produced throughout his career, he co-authored the classic 1957 book The Dynamics of Interviewing, with Robert Kahn. Cannell was a fellow of the American Statistical Association and the American Psychological Association. He was a Fulbright Senior Scholar in 1981, and in 1999 received the Award for Exceptionally Distinguished Achievement from the American Association for Public Opinion Research (AAPOR). The university and the Survey Research Center honors his memory with the Charles Cannell Fund in Survey Methodology, with the goal to "further research and training on the interviewer-respondent interaction and its effects on the validity and quality of survey data."
Sources consulted:
Curriculum Vitae, September 23, 2001 (in Curriculum Vitae and Bibliography folder).
Survey Research Center "Awards from the Charles Cannell Fund in Survey
Methodology" http://www.isr.umich.edu/src/cannellfund.html (as of 10/12/2007).
The Charles F. Cannell Papers measure 2.5 linear feet and range from 1946 to 2001. The bulk of the material, however, dates from 1974 to 1998. Papers consist of project files, research proposals and grant applications, conference presentations, teaching material, and biographical information, the majority of which span 1974 to 1998. The bulk of the collection represents work on an array of projects regarding interviewing and survey methodology, including several projects on the use of technology, such as the telephone, in the interviewing process. The papers have been divided into four series: Biographical Files; Conferences and Seminars Files; Projects and Proposals Files; and Topical Files.
Subjects:
Atomic bomb.; Cannell, Charles F.; Interviewing.; Social sciences--Research.; Social surveys.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Institute for Social Research.; University of Michigan. Survey Research Center.
- Biographical Files 1991-2001
  The Biographical Files, 1991-2001 (0.2 linear feet) pertain to Cannell's career and family history. Material includes several versions of his curriculum vitae, complete bibliography of his published material, lifetime achievement award he received from the American Association for Public Opinion Research (AAPOR), planning documents from the Charles Cannell Fund established at the time of his retirement, and genealogical research on the Cannell family.
  - American Association for Public Research (AAPOR) Award 1999 (Box 1)
  - Charles Cannell Fund 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum Vitae and Bibliography circa 1991-2001 (Box 1)
  - Genealogical Research circa 1997 (Box 1)
- Conferences and Seminars Files 1967-1969, 1987-1998
  The Conferences and Seminars Files, 1967-1968, 1987-1998 (0.5 linear feet) concern the planning and presentations given at several survey research conferences in which Cannell either participated or helped organize. Presentations include a talk given at the American Association for Public Opinion Research (AAPOR) Conference; a paper based on a youth survey concerning technology and the family presented at the American Statistical Association (ASA) Conference; and notes for several talks Cannell delivered at different conferences. Documents concerning the planning of conferences include the International Collaborative Study of Medical Care Utilization (ICSMCU) Conference, for which Cannell served as a consultant; and the Health Survey Research Methods Conference. Cannell served on this conference's planning committee and the file includes grant and administrative material.
  - American Association for Public Research (AAPOR) Conference 1992 (Box 1)
  - American Statistical Association Conference 1993 (Box 1)
  - Health Survey Research Conference 1987-1989, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - International Collaborative Study of Medical Care Utilization (ICSMCU) Conference 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Talks 1994-1998 (Box 1)
- Projects and Proposals Files 1946-1947, 1970-1989
  The Projects and Proposals Files, 1946-1947, 1970-1989 (1.5 linear feet) are organized around 21 research projects and grant proposals. The topics include public opinion surveys Cannell conducted while at the Department of Agriculture's Division of Program Studies. Two of these projects focus on public opinion concerning the atom bomb after the tests on Bikini Island and the public view of the international situation after World War II. These papers include survey material with original interviews, interviewer correspondence, and opinion summaries that help capture the public mood of the late 1940s. The majority of the Projects and Proposals series consists of research conducted while Cannell was on the faculty at the University of Michigan. This material relates to interviewing methodology, survey physiology and technology. Several of these projects focus on telephone surveys and how telephone technology affected the quality of the interview process. Research in this area include the relationship between voice quality and survey refusal rates, several projects on health surveys conducted over the telephone, methods for studying and improving telephone interviewing techniques, and research into computer assisted telephone interviewing. The University of Michigan projects also contain material on housing surveys, the accuracy of automobile accident reporting, and many funding proposals, the bulk of which are requests to the National Science Foundation.
  - Atom Bomb Project
    - Correspondence 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - National Area Sample circa 1947 (Box 1)
    - Proposal 1946 (Box 1)
    - Report 1947 (Box 1)
    - Summary of Findings 1947 (Box 1)
  - Automobile Accident Reporting Project 1973 (Box 1)
  - Computer Assisted Telephone Interviewing (CATI) 1978-1981, 5 folders (Box 1)
  - Computer Assisted Telephone Interviewing (CATI) Conferences 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Housing Survey Project 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Health Service Telephone Project 1979 (Box 1)
  - Health and Social Behavior Project 1979-1980, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - International Situation Project
    - Codes 1946 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1946-1947, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Face Sheets 1946 (Box 1)
    - General Attitudes 1946 (Box 2)
    - "How Three People Think" Paper 1946 (Box 2)
    - Instructions 1946 (Box 2)
    - Interviews 1946, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Pretests 1946 (Box 2)
  - Interviewing Methods 1966-1975 (Box 2)
  - Linked Telephone Project
    - Final Report 1987 (Box 2)
    - Proposal 1985 (Box 2)
    - Survey Material 1985-1986 (Box 2)
  - National Medical Expenditure Survey (NMES) 1987-1988, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - National Science Foundation (NSF) Proposals 1970-1978, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Pretesting Project
    - Final Report 1989 (Box 2)
    - Funding Renewal 1988-1989, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Papers 1989 (Box 2)
    - Proposal 1986-1988, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Retiree Housing Project 1991-1992 (Box 2)
  - Telephone Committee 1974-1984, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Telephone Data Collection Project 1978-1979 (Box 2)
  - Telephone Methodology Project 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Telephone Bibliography 1973-1980 (Box 2)
  - Sources of Information Project circa 1948 (Box 3)
  - Subjective Health Project
    - Proposal 1977 (Box 3)
    - Survey Material 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Voice Quality Project
    - Proposal 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - Reports 1983-1987 (Box 3)
    - Survey Material circa 1983 (Box 3)
- Topical Files 1962-1998
  The Topical Files, 1962-1998, (0.3 linear feet) consist of scattered material concerning Rensis Likert; notes and ideas for articles, including handwritten comments and preliminary drafts; and teaching material consisting of lecture notes, class outlines, and master transparencies.
  - Likert, Rensis L. 1962, 1977-1993 (Box 3)
  - Notes and Article Ideas circa 1969-1974, 1996, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Teaching Material 1982-1998, 3 folders (Box 3)